one of the questions I get asked all the
time is how do you stay in profitable
trades longer and avoid closing them too
early you know there's nothing more
frustrating than closing a profitable
trade too soon and then watching all
that potential profit that you've left
on the table just drift away right
before your eyes but it's something that
most Traders experience all the time and
I've talked about in a previous video
which you can watch up here how most
Traders create these lose lose
situations for themselves so they end up
in this Perpetual state of frustration
but in many cases it's completely
avoidable and all it requires is for you
to make some adjustments to your trading
approach so let me walk you through the
three main things that help me to stay
in profitable trades longer and make the
most of the opportunities that I'm
trading the first thing is a simple rule
that I try to stick to and I always
encourage other traders to try and stick
with this rule as well the rule is
whenever you make a decision or take an
action in the markets you should already
know when or where your next decision
will be made there shouldn't be a moment
when you're in a trade and you don't
know when your next decision needs to be
made because if you do that you're just
going to be reacting to every price move
that happens and end up making decisions
based on knee-jerk reactions or just gut
feeling so your next decision Point
might be based on a certain time or
amount of time that's passed or a
particular price point but either way it
needs to be based on something logical
so for example if your next decision
point is going to be based on time it
would be logical if this is because
that's time is close to the end of your
trading session and you need to make a
decision about whether you're going to
stay in the trade overnight or not or it
might be that there's an economic data
release at 1 p.m. and you want to make
your decision 15 minutes before that
about what action you should take with
your trade whether you're going to scale
out move your stop- loss exit the trade
just hold on and so on and if it's based
on price it should be related to a
logical point in the markets either a
point where you expect a shift in
activity could take place or where the
expectancy of the trade is going to
change in some way
an illogical example would be the points
on the chart where your profit is a
around number like £1,000 that's what a
lot of Traders do you know they'll set
their profit Target or make their next
decision once they've hit ,000 whether
they've planned it or not but that bears
no relation to the opportunity itself
it's not a logical decision point it's
just an emotional one so the idea is
that when you make these decision points
when you set where they're going to be
you then don't make any decisions or
take any actions until that point or
that time is reached otherwise you're
likely to be deviating from the logic of
the situation and just being reactive
based on emotional responses to the
price movements that you're seeing and
of course if your decision points are
leaving you exposed for too much time
then you just need to go through an
optimization process at some point down
the line and fix that so you can have
logical decision points that are not
leaving you exposed for a lengthy amount
of time and missing out on all the
action of the markets and by the way if
your decision is to take no action like
you've decided look okay I'm going to do
nothing I'm going to leave the trade as
it is that still counts as a decision
and you should already know where your
next decision point is going to be never
leave it open-ended a few years ago I
released a video that's completely about
this rule so if you want to go into more
detail have a bit more depth just click
the video that's linked up here but the
thing is many Traders can't follow this
rule because of the way that they're
trading they use something that I call a
setup based approach which you may have
heard me refer to before it means that
the entire opportunity relies solely on
the setup itself so in other words they
find a setup for a trade and when they
enter that trade they set their
stop-loss and their profit Target and
then it's like set and forget hope for
the best now a lot of the time the
profit Target is also really far from
the price either they're feeling
ambitious about it or greedy it's like a
one to 10 risk reward or even higher
than that and technically they're meant
to just leave the trade to either hit
their stop loss or their take profit
level so they're hoping that that setup
that they found is is enough to cause
that hugely asymmetric move the problem
is a lot can happen between your entry
point and a profit Target that's far
from the current price the context of
the market could change events could
take place like economic events or the
price might just hit an area where a
shift in activity is expected and
without these things being factored into
your trade strategy you're just leaving
yourself exposed and this is why a lot
of Traders end up closing their trades
too soon because they can sense
intuitively that there are things that
they're not accounting for in their
analysis of the opportunity they can
sense that the market has changed since
they set up and waiting for that profit
Target might not make sense anymore but
at that point since it's not part of
their plan either they wait for the
profit Target regardless of what happens
or they trade based on a gut feeling
which might not be logical might not be
the best thing for the opportunity so
they're caught in this kind of Catch 22
situation so instead you can Factor all
of this into the way you analyze the
opportunity and plan your trade so you
can have more frequent decision points
while still keeping them logical and all
of this relates to the second thing that
stops me from closing profitable trades
too early estimating the probabilities
of potential outcomes when you enter a
trade with a setup based approach you're
making a statement whether you realize
it or not that there are only two
meaningful potential outcomes for the
next price moves the negative outcome
which is where it moves to your stop
loss or the positive outcome where it
reaches your profit Target but what
about all the things in between like we
just discussed like what if the price
moves heavily into a profit for you but
it hasn't quite reached your AAR profit
Target instead your up F Bar and the
price interacts with a path of
resistance where you expect an activity
change to take place like interacting
with an order block of some sort so the
price then may move all the way against
you and lead to a loss because it didn't
reach your profit Target that's a
potential outcome that you could have
planned for that's not facted into your
setup based approach and when this
happens more than one time you start
getting that gut feeling every now and
then that maybe you should close your
trade too early but at that point it's
not necessarily logical you don't have
any sort of basis for it so you're going
against your trading plan you kind of
caught between two different ideas there
so instead I use a context based
approach where my decisions are always
based on the next logical potential
outcomes so maybe I think that
ultimately the price will eventually
reach all the way up here but I know
that there are a number of areas that
could lead to a shift in activity
between the entry price and that point
over there so there are a bunch of
potential outcomes along the way so I
can assess where those potential
outcomes are and then estimate the
probabilities of each of the outcomes
playing out I start with the first order
outcomes which is the immediate move and
then I look at the second order outcomes
as a conditional probability of the
first order outcome and so on and so on
and this achieves a few important things
for us firstly it allows us to figure
out the expectancy of the trade based on
different orders of outcomes so we can
tell if it's a viable opportunity in the
first place if you even should be
trading that secondly it shows us that
the further we go from the current price
the further out we go the more
inaccurate our probability estimates
will be so when you have a profit Target
that's like 10 r or further you're
likely relying on luck a lot more than
you think unless you're talking about
like a long-term opportunity for which
you have solid fundamental analysis
where you've assessed all potential
outcomes assigned probabilities to each
of those and so on that's a different
story I'm talking about with technicals
and the third thing is that it allows
you to hold on to the trade for much
longer and wait for those outcomes to
play out because when you've estimated
the probability of an outcome it changes
your mindset in fact it changes the way
your brain processes and we've talked
about that in a previous video as well
but you're no longer trying to guess
when you should get out of the trade to
make sure that you can Bank a profit
instead you're trusting in your
probability estimates and letting the
outcome play out regardless whether it's
in your favor or not and then you can
calibrate your accuracy over time the
accuracy of your probability estimates
to ensure that you're getting more and
more accurate so you can depend on these
estimates more and more in future now if
this is your first time hearing me speak
about all of this well first of all
welcome to the channel but also I'm sure
you have questions and objections and
things like that so if you want to know
a lot more about this approach check out
the link below to my free master class
which is a lot longer and a lot more
detailed and it's likely to address a
lot of these areas that you're not sure
about so hopefully you can see now how
these first two tips work hand inand a
context based approach means you're
looking at the next potential outcomes
and making a decision about your trade
based on those now in most cases a
logical decision point will be once an
outcome has played out then you can
assess the next first order outcomes and
Beyond to figure out the expectancy and
see if it makes sense to carry on
holding the trade to exit to make a risk
adjustment either by moving your stop
loss or scaling in scaling out that kind
of thing is based on the outcomes and
that brings me on to the final tip if
you're using this approach your decision
to scale out of the trade will be based
on the next potential outcomes and what
that means for the expectancy of your
trade and whether you need to reduce
your risk but if I want to hold a
profitable trade for longer I'll
sometimes scale out of the trade even if
it doesn't fit the logic of the
opportunity instead it's logical from a
psychological point of view so when you
scale out of a trade it satisfies your
need for instant gratification and other
psychological factors it's the
equivalent of a kid taking a nibble of
the marshmallow in the Stanford
marshmallow experiment and then waiting
for the second marshmallow after that so
if I think that I should be holding the
trade longer but I'm feeling that urge
to bank a profit which is completely
normal I mean we're all human we have
those feelings like loss aversion
instant gratification and so on well I
can just take a nibble off the trade to
satisfy that urge and let the rest of
the trade run so even if it's not
logical for the opportunity I'll
sometimes do that anyway just knowing
that otherwise I'm going to get in my
own way and if you want to know more
about that and some more tips for
letting profitable trades run that
relate more to the psychological side of
things I'd recommend watching this video
next thanks for watching